[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to the show tanmai hey hey
everybody hey jeff thanks for having me
absolutely glad you're here so let's
dive right in what is graphql and why
should our listeners know more about it
that's a that's a question so let me
i have i have layers of answers for that
question so let me start with what
graphql is right so graphql is an api
specification similar to the way rest is
an api specification similar
another kind of api specification right
so so graphql is just another api
specification
where it's intended for and optimized
for a few particular use cases but at
its core it's an api specification now
this was an api specification that got
developed at facebook in the earlier in
in the last decade and then they open
sourced it around 2016 as developers
kind of started really
enjoying it and liking it and taking to
it there was the creation of the graphql
foundation which was a part of the linux
foundation within the cncf and we're
also founding members and a bunch of
early facebook bunch of earlier adopters
some early vendors in the ecosystem all
kind of came together and founded that
graphical foundation to help govern the
specification and help it evolve over
the coming years so that at its core is
what graphql is it's an api
specification now we'll talk about why
this api specification exists and why
people are excited about it and why you
should also be excited about it as a
listener so
now kind of what when you it sits the
same layer as an api specification as
where http address apis do for this kind
of use case that you have when
front-endish applications are talking to
back-end apis right it sits at that
layer it was intended to sit at that
layer you can like you can use any api
specification for doing anything so you
can obviously do that but that's kind of
where it started off so where it started
off was when you load the facebook
application you use the facebook app
after you log in
maybe you're on your news feed and
you're looking at your news feed right
that api call that's getting that news
feed started using graphql buddies right
and that's kind of evolved there and
today also when you see kind of
graphical being used in most places
people are using it for for as a better
api specification for their applications
to talk about back-end systems now when
you think about this api and think about
kind of what happens when you use this
api as put yourself in the shoes of this
application developer or the team that's
writing these api calls to fetch data
from the back end essentially or to make
api calls to fetch api results right and
render that on your application when
you're doing that you run into a few
kind of
common challenges
that are very irritating as a developer
so if you think about like this
challenge if you're rendering the screen
maybe it's an ecommerce application
right and
you want to show the profile of this
user right and so you're showing a
profile of this user of the end user
that has the name email stuff like that
it has their last five addresses
it has their recent transactions right
maybe a bunch of other relevant
information that you want to have for
this user on their profile page now if
you're building this application out
you'll realize that to service this
application you'll have to make multiple
api calls to fetch this because
just the way that the ecosystem has
panned out and the way the industry is
shaped up is that
there is an api development team that
builds apis and gives them to you and
because it's a different team you have
to talk to them to get apis and they
build apis right so there's obviously
because it's a different team it's a
different set of humans we're building
api endpoints and giving them to you and
so when you get to this i this time of
building this application this profile
screen you're looking at a different api
endpoint for a profile like you're
fetching the username and then you're
hitting a different api endpoint for
their transactions you're getting a
different api endpoint for the last like
their last five credit cards right so
you're hitting these different api
endpoints oh yes the endless problem of
endpoint proliferation
exactly right and and so as an
application developer like you're making
these api calls you're integrating them
and you run into all sorts of these
problems that you don't want to solve
right like you're like man if this api
returns in 100 milliseconds and then
this one returns in 500 milliseconds and
then this one is really flaky
how do i get them to render at the same
time do i block all rendering right or
do i wait for it to incrementally render
because that's the nature of this right
you can run into problems like that
you'll often run into problems where
you're like man this profile endpoint
returns a hundred attributes
i don't want to get 100 attributes i
really this is a mobile screen i just
need to show username and email right i
don't need these 100 properties of this
user why are we eating up the network
like it's slower it's expensive
why are we doing that if if i just want
to show username and email right and
then
now now all of these problems are
solvable for example you can go and talk
to the api development team and say can
you give me an endpoint that is just
exactly what i need for my screen
but you know like humans don't like
talking to each other right like clearly
you've seen that happen all across the
world or even if they do it doesn't
necessarily mean communication is
happening exactly people are talking at
each other right yeah so man that's good
i got a little extension but you know
that this happens right you have you
have this application development team
and they're like give me a better api
and then it takes six weeks for you to
give them a spec of what api you want
which is that one api that gets you all
of the data that you want and only the
data that you want and then they build
it and then they send it back to you and
we still haven't really solved api
documentation right everybody just sort
of does it in a different way
they have different practices around it
some people use open api specs some
people use a google sheet some people
use things like a postman and share a
collection with you of their api
endpoints right like there's just too
many different ways of doing things
which means that this idea of like
requesting this unique api endpoint and
then somebody giving that endpoint to
you and then documenting it and like
every time a tiny part of the shape
changes or or you know and then there's
actual integration concerns about they
didn't document the types properly right
maybe they're serializing it from python
and they used a weird library that
returns a boolean with a capital t r u e
as a string instead of returning it is a
json true that's serialized like as per
the json specification and you realize
that error like when you got the api
endpoint that's not how it was
documented
like death by a thousand cuts for this
is like you don't want to worry about
all of this right so graphql came up as
a
more coherent way of addressing these
problems more systematically right and
and that kind of this is where draft
will started of course there's like any
new thing that you create it's a new
abstraction there'll be more there's
things to think about there's trade-offs
and there's stuff like that but you know
that that was kind of the setting or
where the world was when we decided or
when when the community kind of looked
at hey cross ql could be a really
elegant way to solve these problems but
you know that's that's how graphql
started so basically to sum up some of
the things you said previously you could
use any form of api specification to
define apis as you mentioned before but
there's obviously trade-offs and pros
and cons which as we know is you know
software engineers it's all just
trade-offs
but some of the trade-offs you mentioned
are things like difficulty with
consistent documentation and endpoint
proliferation and difficulties of
communication between front and back and
team and and then the need to have
specific apis which sounds brittle and
fragile and so generally speaking it
seems like some smart people had this
idea to say what if we could take
something more akin to what martin
fowler calls a specification pattern to
find search criteria on the client and
then enable the system that's responding
to those client requests to apply those
criteria on behalf of the client is that
correct exactly
right it's exactly like that it's it's
exactly kind of motivated with that
sense in mind and the reason why
craftskill became really popular with
these developers because it also hit
upon an interesting
thing that we have as developers today
is that
the de facto kind of communication
standard between systems has become json
and graphql is shamelessly all about the
json it's all about making it convenient
to
query that the set of endpoints that you
have
that respond with json and for you to
consume that json right and that that
experience is really really nice of
learning graphql and using graphql
because it's about that because it's
about json and that also has tradeoffs
when it comes to non json information
but that's kind of what makes graphql
really nice to use as well and one of
the big reasons behind why it became
popular as opposed to so many other ways
of solving that problem with rest with
enhancement stores with conventions on
top of rest with entirely different
solutions as well that's one of the
reasons why kraftwere also became really
popular because json was just becoming
this defacto and is kind of like this de
facto way of exchanging data between
decoupled systems yeah that's really
interesting so i imagine as you're
defining your graphql api you mentioned
documentation before so i'm sure we'll
get a little bit more into that as we go
but people need to know what they have
access to
so talk a little bit about
how you define your graphql api and then
can listeners read to it i guess the
answer is yes but can they write to it
and let's explore those topics for for a
little bit that one of the key things
about graphql right and so
let's take the analogy back to the rest
world where imagine that you're building
a rest api endpoint right how would you
build it you would write a piece of code
that is served over a web server right
there's a path that is attached to when
the pass is called by your web server it
hits a function people that a controller
say that function is a piece of code
that executes some logic that returns
some data and json right and the
parameters are that you're taking it
over a url path you're taking some url
parameters maybe you're taking a json
payload as some input and perform some
logic and you return with some output
right now graphql is
a very very similar idea the idea is
that now somebody sends you a query the
parameter is now query right it's not a
pass and like query params and a json
file it's actually a query so think of
it as like i'm posting to this endpoint
that says query
user user.id user.email right so if you
look at graphql it kind of looks like
the query that you're sending to the
server is the json that you would want
but only the keys of the json that you
would want so imagine that the json that
you wanted was
a user object that had id as a key value
name as a key and value if that's the
response you wanted the query that you
send is user open brace id comma email
close press that's the query that you
send so you're sending it the skeleton
of the response that you want now the
first thing the web server does when it
receives this graphql query is that it
maps
fields that you see to functions so it
takes the user and it says
what function in my code can process
this user field right and then the
control starts process runs the logic of
of trying to get the user information
and get only id and email as responses
and then that function
runs and decides what to do so so that's
that's kind of broadly how graphql works
nothing earth-shakingly different right
it's it's just defining a pattern for
how you would take that query map it to
different functions that you have so
when you think about graphql and you
have
user.transactions user dot saved cards
it's essentially calling these functions
in like a depth first search way right
so you hit users you call the user
function then you call the transactions
function then you call the save cards
function so you call these different
functions it returns the right bits of
data and then that becomes the final
json and that json gets sent out again
nothing particularly magical just fairly
straightforward yeah sounds very simple
although later on i'm sure we'll dig a
little bit more into the n plus one
problem that listeners are probably
considering there exactly so that kind
of explains the reading side now how
about on the person building the graphql
api how do they go about actually
defining the schemas that can service up
these these queries yep that's a that's
a very good question so there's a
variety of ways that you'll see in the
ecosystem for how that final schema
comes together originally and this is
the approach that facebook took when
they built craft ql they already had a
lot of these functions that would return
various entities right and so as they
would build a new function so if i built
a transactions function right or i build
a transactions model that is connected
to the user's model and i'm writing a
function for for being able to extract
transactions or fetch that user's
transactions the act of me writing that
function that piece of code would
automatically create a graphql schema so
you're writing your you're creating
these entities you know that define your
api
and from that definition and as you
write them the graphical schema kind of
gets spit out automatically right and
that graphql schema essentially contains
your entire it's your definition of
those users users have this type and
then users have transactions and
transactions are 10 attributes and
safeguards have 100 attributes and these
are the different types and stuff like
that right so that becomes the schema
the act of creating those functions or
those controllers or those entities
creates the schema there are within that
also there are many different approaches
you can go model first you can go
function first right there is there is
then another popular approach which is
that you start with the graphql schema
itself so you start by saying what do i
want my schema to be i want my schema to
be users that has these five attributes
and transactions and whatnot so you
define the schema first
and then you write each of those
functions
that are basically
that back those schema right so you're
right because you had a schema that had
users transactions cards you'll now have
a function that has a user's function a
transactions function or parts function
right the approach that third approach
is like a metadata approach which is the
approach that we take at hasura which is
that you define the metadata of it's a
declarative way of defining what your
different models are and how to access
those models what the sources of those
models are and then a system like
hustler automatically creates the
graphql api for that definition of
models right so you can have a variety
of methods just like you would for rest
as well yeah that's interesting as
you're saying that now i i know
if listeners or anything like me or some
of them they hear the word orm and some
of them run headed for the hills and and
others can't imagine life without them
and so there's kind of a strong
separation there i think in the
community i'm not sure if it's 50 50 but
it's definitely strongly you know
separation there and it does sound like
a little bit like the metadata
approaches approach so i don't say that
disparagingly because but it does have
some relationship i think and so let's
pause on that a little bit uh when we
get further into the show i want to
explore that a little bit more so you've
kind of now described how we send our
queries how we sort of define these
models and the different ways of doing
that which is interesting api first
metadata these sorts of things defining
your functions
so that's all the reading side now
if i have a rest api i could make a
read-only rest api but it's often useful
to be able to do things with my rest api
as well yeah so let's talk about can you
write to graphql could you always write
to graphql and can you now let's explore
that a little bit yeah that's a very
good question and it's often something
that people don't think about when they
think about graphql because they're like
here 90 of my workload is read graphql
is great for linux let me just use it
for trades but of course graphql also
has a story for rights and graphical
calls and mutations now when you look at
the rest restish or restful kind of
conventions you use http verbs right so
you'd say get a resource and then you
have a post endpoint which is the idea
of being able to
go in and you know create something
right you have put to go in and replace
something you have delete and you have
these different kinds of http verbs with
different endpoints and different
payloads that you use as kind of a loose
convention to define what you want to do
now it's just a convention is important
to remember right you could also
technically have a get endpoint that's
actually writing data don't do that yes
don't do that don't do that but you
could right because
it's just ultimately just strings and a
convention right although you can't send
it to body so you'd be getting all that
from the query string which is even more
gross but i digress yeah exactly exactly
exactly but i mean so technically you
could get it from the body but again
don't do that like
don't write a web server that for a get
endpoint peeks into the payload right
because you should not be expecting a
payload right so when you're so with
graphql the idea was that we just have
one
end point and typically people implement
it as a post endpoint that will take a
graphical query and processing now when
i send a graphql query that describes
the skeleton shape i was talking about
that becomes a read query in that
payload if i now when i start that query
instead of using the word query if i
started with the word mutation that then
defines that i'm doing a right a right
kind of activity so i'm doing something
that will mutate state potentially
graphql says
the craft fuel convention is you use
queries for the query keyword which is
reading and mutation for the mutation
the mutation keyword is that you want to
write stuff now that mutation could be
insert update delete it could do a bunch
of things we don't care about
a more granular specification we only
care about the fact that it's a mutation
and the way of mutation gets represented
in graphql is also pretty
straightforward the way for example a
create user mutation would look like
it's a mutation
and then you open up a brace and say
create user and then you specify all the
arguments that you want for create user
so it's a create user name is
name colon name key value pair email key
value pair right those are the arguments
to your creative user and the output
that you expect after that mutation is
you expect the new id maybe you want to
read the username again maybe you want
to read the email again so id username
email
social handles any enrichment that you
did right you want to expect that as the
output so in the graphql world you're
using mutations to
specify these kind of arguments that you
want to do for write and then you're
reading back after the write you're
reading back stuff and you're expecting
a json payload and you use the same kind
of idea that i'm going to specify the
keys that i care about
in that response and so you specify
those keys so you say create user name
email and in the response i want own the
id so it's create username email open
curly brace id and that's your mutation
now
the convention that you would create for
your own api is you would have mutation
create user mutation delete user
mutation update user but all of these
all of those create update insert words
are
it's your api right these aren't the
verbs that are defined exactly
exactly graphql only says mutation and
then steps back and lets you define your
convention so you want to have a kurdish
style thing where it's insert update
delete up to you you want to have
something that's more like actions right
where each like word represents more of
a domain concept that might happen right
like create new user right which is less
crud and more an action that happens
right more like a cqrs type thing like
it's a command that you're kind of
you're invoking a command and that
command can do many things right it's
not a kurdish thing necessarily so
that's your convention basically now
okay so we can read we can write we can
define schemas
and it sounds like two this gets us
closer to i'll have to find the article
that i read recently that talked about
how the internet is built on what's
called the narrow waste and it really
boils down to it's just text it's just
text over
tcp
and of course now they're moving to text
over udp with http 3. and in a similar
way that that's where i think rest apis
have have struggled because they take
away a lot of that narrow waste and they
add a lot of conventions that aren't
always followed and then there's
conventions on conventions and
and all these things and as jim morris
said the wonderful thing about standards
is there's so many of them to choose
from and so it feels like that's sort of
where we've gotten with the with the
rest ish type apis
whereas with graphql it sounds like it's
closer to that narrow waist where it's
query and mutation it's json in it's
json out yep that's it fantastic right
and that makes it very nice i just
wanted to add one more thing jeff that
okay queries also graphql also support
subscriptions which is interesting so
the three keywords in graphql are query
mutation and subscription so
subscription is the idea of being able
to it's like query but you're looking at
events so you're looking at real-time
information that is typically coming in
over web sockets but so those are the
three kind of keywords that graphql has
and then
whatever you want for your domain is the
convention that you can have inside
those three keywords interesting and i
would imagine not every graphql
implementation necessarily supports all
of these
subscriptions for example exactly okay
exactly some graphql apis won't support
mutations they'll only do queries right
now with subscription let's talk about
that a little bit more because that's
new to me and it might be new to some
listeners as well subscription sounds a
bit like a kind of like a pub sub
subscribe yep yep that's the it sounds
it sounds it's it's meant for those
kinds of use cases the idea is that you
might be having a chat application you
might have an api that is requesting a
stream of data you might be subscribing
to a particular comment and watch like
live emojis happen on that comment for
example right these are kind of
situations where you're looking at data
coming in as it comes in from the server
and is sent to the client data that is
coming in from the server as it is sent
to the client now here you'll see that
typically people would want to do this
over web sockets if you were
implementing this for the rest
yourself you you can do a lot there's a
lot of variation possible with how you
would structure that right set up a
websocket client set up a websocket
server the protocol that you want to
have for authentication authorization
how you're going to exchange information
there's a lot of there's a lot to work
with there with graphql subscriptions
you still use web sockets but because
there's a graphical specification the
consumption of these real-time events or
data becomes easy on the client side and
because you're just using a normal
graphical client and you say subscribe
to
user
name and so if username changes you'll
change that on your on your thing right
or you'll say subscribe to messages on
this channel and as messages come in you
know you will fire like a hook on your
client side or something and then you'll
render them as it comes in right and
that just becomes a nicer integration
experience you still have to do the hard
work
of
having a graphql server that can
actually fetch data from a stream that
can do the authorization work you still
need to build that part out but at least
from a protocol point of view from the
client and server setup point of view
some of that has been standardized and
has been taken away from kind of what
you have to worry about but you still
have to do the hard work of doing the
pubs up yeah well and that's what a good
abstraction does is it puts the hard
work where it belongs which is on the
person shipping the api and not on the
person integrating with the api exactly
we've explored a lot of topics about how
you define your schemas with graphql the
fact that it can read it can write you
can even have subscriptions you know
talk about queries mutations and
subscription
what kind of things would you put a
graphq graphql api on top of that's a
really good question
you can put a graphql api on top of
anything if you're willing to do the
work of
building the code that can not just kind
of process the query but understand from
processing the query how to actually go
fetch the data from various sources
right so if you're willing to do that
work you could put a graphql api in
anything that you want right so for
example you can build your own graphql
api even but you can also put your
graphql api on nothing right just like
an api it can be a graphql api that
literally just creates data out of code
right it's like randomly creating some
data and sending some data to you like a
fake api just for testing the api
surface area yeah exactly right you can
you can have a graphql api that does
that you can have a graphql api that you
that ultimately goes and talks to a
database like a postgres database or any
relational database you can put it on
top of a nosql database or a graph
database right any anything that's
actually a backing store of data i
recently over the weekend implemented a
graphql api that lets you query your
operating system so i can do query
processes
uid
process name right statistics about the
process yeah but i in my z shell i've
got ps aux like what do i need no i'm
kidding that's actually really cool
yeah exactly so but but but you know
what you just said is the crux of it you
already have psa
pipe through crap and do whatever you
want so why would you build a graphql
api which is exactly the question that
you should be asking do i need to be
sticking a graphql api on top of this
thing and i think that's really the crux
of it right it's like there are two big
reasons to
want to do that the first is you have a
bunch of application developers
at what i call the edge right you have
developers who are increasingly building
applications at the edge now the edge is
kind of just this evolution of mobile
web serverless
workers right stuff that is kind of
happening in a different security
context and a different performance
context from where the rest of your
centralized kind of data and logic is
right it's the decentralized data and
logic processing part of your of your
business right now those developers when
they want to access the stuff like you
said the narrow waste is http the
narrowest is json right
give them that access over graphql and
they love you for it for example if you
were building an application that showed
your web ui that showed you what
processes
were running on
you know your data center or machine for
whatever reason right now they would
want it over json right like you
wouldn't want them to send in cli
console commands or whatever
on the screen and then get that
responses std out text and then have the
browser process it you might as well
send it over http and you might as well
have a json query language
for sending the payload and getting the
responses and that that makes for an
easier experience all the way around so
whenever you kind of start reaching
those scenarios where people want to
consume these apis especially at the
edge graphql becomes a really nice way
of exposing that data right and then you
can decide what to stick graphical on
top of okay
so like anything else we mentioned
before there's trade-offs and you've
kind of touched a little bit on some use
cases that graphql can be useful for but
let's dive a little bit into some of the
trade-offs because the risk with any new
tool is people treat it as the tool
and then you know the next thing you
know we've got some of the problems that
we tend to have in the software industry
repeating themselves over and over again
and of course we all know what the
definition of insanity is in that
context
so as we talk about trade-offs and use
cases let's talk about first performance
and caching so for sure obviously you
know performance is
one of those things where people always
say performance performance but
obviously it's a concern here and and
listeners might wonder like well i know
how to build rest apis i know how to
make the performance so so how do i deal
with performance and caching in a
graphql context yeah that's a that's a
really good question i would say that
the the fundamental source of the
trade-offs in graphql is that
we flipped control of what data is being
fetched to the client
right you're in a rest world you as the
api developer decide
what data your consumer is going to get
in the graphql world the graphql client
decides what data they want to finish
now this is in a sense the root cause of
all trade-offs all of the cons and the
complexities of graphql come from all of
the pros of graphql also come from that
which is that the client can decide what
they want but you know all the cons also
come from that fundamental decision that
the client decides so when you when we
talk about performance and caching as
soon as you let the client decide what
data they want to get from these apis or
100 api endpoints and they what would
people have had a hundred different api
en points but now they've collected into
one query and now they're getting the
data the challenge for performance is
because you don't know what data the
client wants up front
you might resolve you might have very
inefficient ways of fetching that data
because you don't know what data you
want up front for example if i knew that
you want user and transactions upfront i
can make a really optimized query to the
database or to whatever source i have to
fetch exactly users and transactions
right i'll do a join because i know that
my database can handle these joins very
well or i won't do a join if i know that
my database can't handle joins very well
or if it's a geo distributed database
i'll share it appropriately i'll know
what to do
right because i know the shape of the
data that you want up front but as soon
as i don't know what data you want
because you can do user or transactions
you can do user transactions these are
safe cards now i have to make sure that
this backend system that i'm building
i'm able to fetch the various sources
that i have
as optimally as possible and kind of
create an optimal query plan and create
an optimal data fetching route now
there's a many different ways of
approaching this for example the
approach that we've taken and that's
what we'll see in the industry as well
is we've segmented it into three
different categories of how you can
optimize for this kind of data fetching
if you know that this data is coming
from the same source you execute a
different kind of plan which is
more oriented around doing joins and
doing json aggregations in the same
source if you know that the data is
coming from two different data sources
which are two databases we do you can
you can employ techniques that are
similar to what people have done in the
data virtualization space where they
said how do i take this one sql query
that's actually fetching data from two
places how do i create temporary tables
do efficient joins across databases to
kind of fetch data and then the third is
when you have two entirely disparate
systems you have a rest api that's
giving you users and you have a database
that's giving you transactions or
another rest api that's giving you
transactions so what you do here is this
has been called the data loader pattern
by the graphql industry which is that
you do memoization or port request
caching so there are different kind of
approaches that you can take depending
on how you're fetching data from where
so that's kind of on the data fetching
side does that make sense
it does and it reminds me a bit of how
relational databases have a query
planner and in this case it does sound a
bit like you're having to do some of the
query planning especially when you're
dealing with disparate data sources
because at that point yeah unless
somebody comes up with this technology
and maybe you know hasura is going to do
this in some way but anyways somebody
had to come up with some abstraction
that allows you to do that and let's not
even worry about that for now because
that sounds pretty exactly pretty crazy
exactly exactly and on the caching front
it's fairly similar where
the existing caching infrastructure does
break down when it comes to graphql
because what we kind of assumed as a
industry as a convention was that we use
get
for fetching data and so what happens is
that everything like your cdns
you know your cloud infrastructure your
clients everybody kind of respects the
fact that you know your cash get results
potentially and you'll have cash headers
on them and you'll have these get
endpoints and they'll be cached at
various layers right so potential when
you're making a request you might not
even be hitting the final database or
the final web server that response might
come in from some one of those layers in
the middle whether it's a cdn it's a
varnish cache it's a reddest thing
whatever it is because that's been the
convention now with graphql that becomes
a little bit hairy because your
infrastructure in the middle has to be
changed to understand that you're going
to be potentially caching post requests
because you're sending a query payload
right or you have to
before you ship graphql to production
you want to make sure that you getify
all your queries so instead of doing a
post and a query endpoint you do
something like a get endpoint and you
send it a query hash
like an identifier of the query and the
server knows
has a pre-registered list of queries
that the client is registered and is
able to service that so you leverage
your get infrastructure but it's one of
the things that people are building and
figuring out and having different
approaches to server side caching well
that's interesting too because what you
just described there that puts still the
power in the hands of the client
of which queries they're going to send
but if they pre-register those queries
now they can simplify what they have and
of course i'd recommend as i always do
you create an sdk for this api so
they're not having to do all this
manually exactly and then the hash just
gets flowed automatically and they don't
have to worry about the hash exactly but
the beauty of that now is two now your
system team is able to say which queries
have been registered and they can do
some
checks and pre-optimizations and these
sorts of things instead of oh we're
going to get some random query we don't
know about so now you kind of exactly
this basically is now that communication
is going to happen and it's going to
happen asynchronously and it's going to
happen automatically between the systems
exactly instead of between the people
exactly right and that is that is a
recommended best practice especially if
you're building
applications where
where you know those query structures as
you as you're building the application
now this doesn't work in those scenarios
where
the api surface area is meant to be
dynamic right like for example your
product is an api you your business the
api is a product that you sell to
developers who are outside your
organization and they're doing something
else with it maybe they're building
services with it they're ingesting that
maybe they're building applications but
you know you don't own it you don't know
in those cases you don't want you do
want to give them a flexible api and let
them query for whatever they want and so
when you think about how to cash when
you think about security kind of things
you have to have different ways of
thinking about it right maybe you have
like a an execution quota right that
they get on on the kinds of queries they
can run you get like 500 milliseconds to
the minute you get 500 milliseconds of
query execution time every minute so you
know make a complex query make a simple
query but you have 500 milliseconds of
execution time so that could become the
security paradigm that you want to have
when you do want to expose a dynamic api
okay good to know again more trade-offs
exactly
and that kind of leads a little bit now
into security approaches and
implications so for example
which user is calling this api and maybe
there's certain properties like
personally identifying information or
credit card numbers or passwords which i
i don't know i'm i'm like should you
really put the credit card number in a
get from a graphql api but that you know
whatever but certain information where
maybe certain people can access it and
certain people can't or certain systems
can access
other systems can't so how does graphql
kind of approach the security
implications of
who can see what yeah that's so that's a
very good question the short answer is
graphql doesn't care so graphql says
you do security
we give you an api specification that
lets you define how you want to fetch
data how you're mutating stuff or you're
subscribing to stuff you do security the
way you need to so it ends up
essentially
i think breaking down into the common
layers that you would have to when you
think about api security anyway you
think about what i call authorization
which is who gets access to what
entities
and then exactly what you were saying
jeff
you then have a layer of authorization
which then defines like for example the
first layer of authorization is
i'm trying to fetch this account
can i even access this account model yes
i'm the account owner or the account
manager so i do get access to this
account the second layer of
authorization is what fields do i see on
that model right do i get to see the
fields vanilla as they are do i see all
the 100 attributes of the model do i see
only 50 and then for some of them do i
see derived version of that maybe i see
a token instead of the credit card
number right right i just get lost four
digits i don't get the whole number so
maybe i'm getting transformations or
hidden properties of that so there's
kind of that aspect of security which is
authorization then there's kind of the
authentication aspect of security which
is typically handled outside the graphql
server maybe at your api gateway or
something like that that knows how to
process jwt tokens or cookies and
convert them into session information
that your graphql server can then handle
and inject into its authorization right
so that when the graphql server gets a
query for users it can convert it to a
select star from user where user id
equal to session id right and it can do
that but the authentication piece is
done by the api gateway and then the
third piece which is
unique to graphql that as an ecosystem
we're still trying to figure out what
are different ways of approaching that
are the typical kind of api security
practices that you would have wanted to
have which are a little bit outside
strictly authentication or authorization
and these are things like rate limits
slow loris attacks web socket attacks
right denial of service issues
distributed service issues large like
response payload issues right yeah
either during requested responses like
those kinds of things that are kind of
at that very front of
the api kind of your api stack it's the
edge of your api stack which will
frequently have to contend with these
problems now most of it you can apply
techniques that you would have had from
just your rest world they would have to
have a little bit of modification
because you're breaking some conventions
around get and post and stuff like that
you're posting queries for reading and
writing so you have to evolve that a
little bit
from a logging and monitoring point of
view of knowing that there are security
breaches or events you might want to
evolve that infrastructure a little bit
i think most of it works with that
evolution the part of it that i've
always found very interesting is query
complexity or rate limiting based on
complexity which i find just like a
fascinating space to think about which
is that you you are giving people a
dynamic surface area the query on
you can't use your usual ways of
thinking about rate limits which is 100
api calls per minute because that sort
of doesn't make sense right because it's
not we don't know what the api endpoint
is we want to give that control to the
user so how do we create a nicer
rate limiting abstraction that works for
this kind of flexibility in craft ui so
i think that's kind of a place which is
new but everything else sort of works
yeah and that's challenging too because
i could think of you could have a a
request that returns essentially one
record you know i know and think in
relation we're talking json yeah you
could have request returns a record but
the cost could be incredibly high and so
you might want to rate limit by cost and
of course you know relational databases
have query planners and cost
calculations and these sorts of things
which are all different but the idea is
there but rest api arrest apis they
don't they don't have that notion yeah
and then of course you want to limit by
total amount of content or maybe how
deep the the structured graph is
that definitely sounds like a very
interesting challenge yeah and you know
it's like one of those things where rest
is easier in those respects because when
you've created the rest end point that
returns one record but it's very
expensive you know that it's expensive
yes so because you know that it's
expensive you can assign a static rate
limit to it but when that same record is
a part of a graphql api query you know
somebody might be fetching just that
record somebody might be fetching that
record with other things
right now you might want to have
different rate limits when it's a part
of the thing but it's independently
fetched ah that becomes complicated
that's right and you're shifting the
complexity down to the system behind the
api which is the right thing to do
because that's technical empathy for
your end user but that does also bring
new challenges and trade-offs exactly
which exactly i think leads us to a good
next uh next topic which is to avoid the
graphql all the things approach that you
know people might try to do
when is graphql not the right solution
yeah i think today there's a pretty
simple answer to that which is that
graphql is not a good solution if you if
your data is not json okay so if your
data is video data binary data file data
right and it's not json that's just an
immediate cutout for graphql graphql is
not a good fit but apart from that there
would be some use cases also where i'd
say that graphql might not be a
phenomenal fit for example if you have
an extremely right heavy workload right
you're pushing stuff continuously into a
pipe for example say you have iot
devices that are continuously emitting
data right you have systems that are
emitting logs that are just writing into
something and you're not really reading
you don't have a read load
graphql is overkill at that point right
don't use mutate for that i think is
what you're saying that's not the yeah i
mean yeah because if you're if your api
is 90 muted and 10 query you lose the
benefits of graphql because graphql is
designed to optimize the query pass yes
it was designed to handle the mutate
path but it wasn't really optimized for
the mutation experience it was optimized
for the query experience right and so if
you just have a 90 10 kind of split then
you know you probably you don't have to
use graphql right and you might benefit
from not using graphql and using a
format that is more efficient because
there's interesting trade-offs with the
right heavy workloads right
it's a different subset of use cases so
so i would say broadly i would say those
those are the two places where graphical
might not be a good fit things that are
not json and things that are very very
heavy now how about internal versus
external apis
i think you could get the impression
that this is a way to deliver apis for
application developers but are there use
cases where it makes sense to actually
provide a graphql api for internal
consumption between systems that's a
very good question i would say i think
there's no reason you can't do it for
sure so when it comes to like this
integration between systems it depends
on what you're optimizing for let's say
for example the different systems that
are consumed that are talking to each
other right are talking to each other
in the same kind of
security context
right and the same
they're all running kind of in the same
kind of cloud infrastructure there's no
kind of security implication to what
they're doing there's very little
network latency between these two
systems they can be chatty right for
example you have a server in the same
region as another server and these two
processes can kind of just talk to each
other and they can afford to be chatty
right in those cases you might benefit
from more kind of chatty protocols where
there's back and forth that's
continuously happening something like a
grpc might be more beneficial right but
if these two services that are talking
to each other these two systems that are
talking to each other are cannot afford
to be chatty which comes which basically
boils down to two reasons it boils down
to either because there's a switch in
security context right if the security
contacts are different they can't really
chat with each other as if they write
co-located right right you kind of
frequent back and forth communication
because you're continuously changing the
security context and the second is if
there's a performance implication which
is that there are two services but there
are two services like one is running on
a cloudflare workload and one is running
in your like aws centralized ec2
infrastructure right
they are two processes yes but but they
are there is speed of light issues
they are they are far away from each
other right yes so in those contexts now
graphql can become better because
graphql can allows you to be less chatty
more elegantly right it says well
clearly you can't be very chatty in this
context you do want to fetch a certain
amount of data why don't you as a client
decide what data you want to fetch so
here developers are kind of making more
precise api calls to fetch the
information that they want because they
want to control the amount of data they
send they want to make sure that the
security check is optimized and they're
not triggering 100 security checks
unnecessarily right in a chatty protocol
every record that you fetch you want to
do a security check don't do that if
you're if you're very chatty right like
yeah it's better to put them closer
together and let them talk in unbounded
security context with just each other so
i think it's those kinds of constraints
so i would say when it's service to
service communication the way i like to
think about this graphql is a great fit
when you have centralized systems
talking to decentralized systems
right that's where graphql is is the
perfect fit if you have two systems
within the centralized area or two
systems within the decentralized area i
wouldn't go further i wouldn't reach for
graphql right but when you're going from
like centralized to edge graphical is a
great thing edge to edge central
maybe not and i i would add to that i
think the same could be said of restish
apis as well where when those are used
for internal service to service
communications
it sometimes makes me go a little bit
crazy
but when you're using those for external
it starts to make a lot more sense but
but i digress exactly and because
because the internal external is also
very interesting in what you said
sometimes internal sometimes you could
have internal applications right so
that's different too yes that's correct
that's correct and sometimes you have
systems of systems and there's new
reasons to encapsulate things in various
ways and so again it's all trade-offs
exactly there is no this is always the
right answer in this case but there are
good practices that we can follow as
you're helping us understand
so i imagine with graphql somebody could
just like with the web they could create
their own web server and come with their
own implementations of all of the
standard standards again the constraints
and the verbs and everything like that
and similarly somebody could do the same
graphql but i imagine there's been a
tooling ecosystem that has grown up
around graphql so
maybe share with us a little bit about
the different approaches to tooling
around graphql and what listeners can
expect as they start looking for tooling
in the graphql ecosystem it's very
similar to what you would expect in an
api ecosystem you have client side
tooling you have server side tooling and
then you have collaboration tooling
right those are the categories that will
put it so i would call it client side
tools server side tools and you could
call it sdlc tooling you could call it
collaboration tooling right so those are
the three categories in which you'll
you'll find tooling for graphql in a
within the graphql ecosystem so you have
popular graphql clients what glasgow
clients do is they integrate really well
with your application development kind
of environment maybe it's a web maybe
it's mobile maybe it's a java service
that you're writing so different
languages different devices or platforms
that you're running on you'll have
clients that can basically auto generate
the sdk that you were talking about
right like having an sdk experience for
an api is amazing one of the big wins
for graphql is that graphql clients
automate that sdk experience you can
literally like while you're building a
web application or you're building
something that talks your graphql api
you can just do a sdk dot generator
called the cli command that like
generates the sdk on demand so it takes
the graphql schema and it generates a
typed sdk that integrates really well
with your language and then you can just
with your application development kind
of language and environment and then
works with that so you'll see a set of
tools there you'll see a bunch of tools
in the graphql server side these are
graphql these are things that help you
build graphql servers the work that
we're doing in hustler is kind of in
that one category of tooling that helps
you build different graphql services and
there's again many different approaches
there's graphql as a service kind of
tools there's graphql server tools that
help you literally build graphql servers
from scratch and tooling there and then
of course there's collaboration tools
that are basically api collaboration
tools for graphql your graphql schema is
changing and you want to see how the
graphical schema changes you make
comments to your git repository you want
to trigger certain things that verify
whether the graphql schema has evolved
in a way that might break the schema
like you removed the field from the user
right right and it'll do an automated
check so there's the kind of this sdlc
tooling as well so those are the three
broad categories of tooling that you'll
see in the graphql ecosystem the graphql
ecosystem tooling on the monitoring and
like what i would say the ops front
has
been slower to catch up so it is there
and typically that category of tools the
monitoring and observability and caching
side is starting to grow gradually you
see that kind of that kind of tooling
integrated a little bit with the people
who are and the the community members or
vendors who are building things in the
graphql server side so the graphql
server tools try to also solve for some
of those ops problems
within the kind of the ambit of that
graphql server tool so we noticed that
hopefully over time we start seeing that
separate out a little more you know with
things like open telemetry and whatnot
and graphql specific open telemetry and
stuff like that and that makes sense too
as we talked before about things like
query planning and handling you know
complex queries the ability to monitor
and say hey again it does sound very
similar to what relational databases had
to do but the difference is instead of
it being in a monolithic database server
or even in a sharded you know cluster of
database servers now we're moving the
same problem up but there's similar
challenges and so you need this ability
to monitor see what's going on observe
what's going on and even if you're
getting expensive queries proactively
consider ways that you might be able to
optimize and deliver improvements before
the end user the consumer even complains
about it
exactly exactly yeah okay
well let's talk some about the hasura
solution then what makes hassura unique
in the graphql ecosystem you mentioned a
little bit before that your focus is on
the the server tooling side of things so
talk a little bit about hasura
specifically and why it exists and what
it accomplishes for people who are
interested in using graphql very similar
to kind of some of the themes that we've
been discussing i think are aimed with
as far as to make sure that people get
kind of the benefits of graphql without
having to do some of the heavy lifting
that you have to do when you're building
your own graphical ecosystem so the way
hostile kind of thinks about is what is
the fastest way that we can get you from
these different data sources that you
have
to a production ready graphql api right
so instead of taking hours or days per
api endpoint
we want to do it in like 60 seconds
right you go from 100 models across
four different data sources to an api
within a few days as opposed to kind of
wiring everything up and setting that up
in an effort that might take weeks and
months to kind of take to production
secure add monitoring around it and
stuff like that so that's kind of where
hasta sits it takes a metadata approach
to helping you model the various things
that you have in different types of data
sources and setting up the authorization
rules that's the most important piece of
this to make sure that there's a hasura
has a policy engine
that allows you to specify these
authorization rules for each model what
fields are visible what feeds are hidden
what fields are pii what entities can be
read and why documents can be read if
you're a collaborator or if you're an
editor if the document is public right
those kinds of that policy engine is
what has kind of absorbed and then using
that hustler presents a graphql api that
has conventions around pagination
filtering relationships aggregations
streaming
live queries crud style mutations event
triggers a bunch of stuff that follows a
common convention in how you'd like to
typically interact with those kind of
models so that's kind of where hasra
sits and how visitor works and i will be
very busy creating show notes for all of
the things that you just mentioned so
that listeners can go look those things
up you did mention policy engine i'm
curious if there's any relationship
there to open policy agent or if this is
something history specific this is
something household specific i mean it's
it's it's it's it's open source and we
built the entire thing we launched the
open source engine 2018 and so the
policy engine is is an open source
engine it's most similar to i would say
for those of you familiar with databases
if you're familiar with the rls
engine in databases row level security
engines that certain advanced relational
databases have it's that idea
it's that kind of flexibility and that
idea that we've gotten
okay so looking at your website i see
instant real-time graphql api for
postgresql so clearly there's some
connection here with postgresql as a
supported data source for hasura yeah
but i imagine that's also not the only
data source that hasera supports so
explore a little bit for us why
postgresql is so prominently mentioned
on your website but then also what other
data sources does hasero support clearly
the operating system is one but i
imagine there's others
yeah no so that's a that's a great
question so when we started building
husura we built it only for postcards
because that was made made sense to kind
of choose postcast as a emerging
database its postgres is also
interesting one of those databases that
is now becoming an almost an open
specification
of how a database should behave and the
underlying systems are different if
you're tracking the postgas ecosystem
you'll see not just it's just not just
the postgres database that's become
amazing but you have so many offshoots
of the within the postgres family
whether it's things like yoga by
cockroach
new things like neon.tech which is like
a serverless postgres first offering aws
aurora google recently launched launched
alloy db which again is exact postcards
but optimized for mlai and statistical
workloads right so fascinating kind of
work in the postgres ecosystem made
sense for us to kind of support postgres
as our first data source but over the
years we've added support for sql server
for bigquery and we're now rapidly
adding support for as many data sources
as we can
one of the things we launched recently
along with our open source project was
what we call graphql data connector it's
an api and an sdk that allows any
developer to build support for their own
data source without waiting for hostile
ads support for it and that's in the
context of that is when i built out
support for the operating system so what
i did was i spent an hour customizing or
adding an agent to the back half of
astra's query planning authorization
compilation kind of engine right house
does all of that work and at the final
the final
asp that i get
that is actually the query for a
particular data source i customize that
last bit so that instead of hitting a
database query sql route or a rest api
endpoint i can then fetch whatever i
want and so i customize that bit to
actually fetch from the operating system
and that's how i spend only like a few
hours and i get support for the
operating system
but the graphql api that i get is fully
featured pagination joins authorization
caching security all of that taken care
of and i'm just customizing the last bit
of that like pipeline to fetch that
specific data that i want well you
mentioned ast which for listeners who
didn't catch that that's an abstract
syntax tree which if you've ever taken a
compiler class in computer science
programs you know what that is and
essentially that's another example of a
wonderful abstraction because once
you've compiled down to which by the way
i mentioned open polystation before it's
rules compiled down to an ast that's
actually exactly represented in a json
document because it's all json at the
end and so in a similar fashion if you
can look at this
similar thing you know the system.link
in the dotnet space same thing it
compiles down to an ast exactly and so
that's really interesting that you're
able to do that and really powerful and
so
basically from what you said if hazard
doesn't already support a specific data
source if a listener wants to create a
data source to pull from then knock
yourself out go for it now can they
contribute those back in is there a is
there a trip project or something on
github like
yeah we just started that so you'll see
it on our on our main graphql engine
repo it's just github.com graphql engine
the sdk the connector sdk that we've
released is in alpha right now towards
the end of the year i'm hoping that we
have like a registry that is kind of a
more formal place for people to kind of
maintain and publish different versions
of their connectors right now it's just
full requests that you can put into the
code repo and you go into a directory on
our main thing over time we'll have more
governance around it okay and do you
have examples on github or on your site
that demonstrates sort of when to use
like i imagine that in some cases it
makes sense for people to ship both
rest dish api endpoints as well as
graphql endpoints side by side so you
have some
examples kind of guide listeners in that
area yeah we do we talk about this quite
a bit especially in like harsher
enterprise environments where you can't
just switch api protocols immediately
right they have so many mission critical
systems and so many teams where you want
to do graphql and rest you want to do a
gradual transition maybe you want to do
both for a period of time so several
different examples kind of walking you
through how you can set that up one of
the very interesting things that we
built was an ability for you to create
rest end points
out of graphql instantly so you create
the graphql api first you get this hyper
flexible surface area but then what you
do is when you're you're working with
specific api customers clients
applications that prefer a rest api you
can bang out rest apis really really
quickly you create the graphical query
and you name it and that becomes a
resting point so you're like oh here's a
slash user endpoint and then that's
backed by a particular graphql query
declarative rest api based on a graphql
underpinning spot on very thin that's
exactly it yes and less time writing
controllers and actions and and
exactly right and then that works with
all of your best infrastructure as well
so that works particularly well when you
have a lot of investment on the oxide on
the infrastructure side and the id side
which is already around rest right so
let's talk about deployment and
integration with hysura i know that like
a lot of open source projects there's
both a community edition and an
enterprise edition so maybe talk about
the differences and then of course
self-hosted versus cloud hosted so maybe
share with listeners as they want to get
started how can they get started on
their own and then what would cause them
to want to move up to another level with
either a hosted environment or an
enterprise license no that's a that's a
really good question so the easiest way
to try hasero out is to just pull down
the docker container if you have an
existing data source point that to the
data source you know whenever you can
run a container you can run
it stateless and clusters automatically
so that you can you know run one
instance you can scale that out and run
a hundred different instances of faster
we're going to be publishing a benchmark
that talks about our streaming
subscriptions and scaling to one million
streaming subscriptions with like you
know i think 70 instances of hustler or
something and so you can you can kind of
do that with our containers and exactly
like just said you can run our manage
cloud service where we run these for you
in the vpc of your choice or in a
multi-tenant environment on your cloud
vendor so that that's kind of a managed
service you don't have to run sort of
managers or scale it up or down or
customize it for workloads and then you
can run it yourself now as you kind of
move up various tiers on our cloud
offering or if you move from open source
to you know a self-hosted enterprise
version what we want to ensure is that
in a machine in a mission critical kind
of deployment the total cost of
owning and delivering your api is as
conveniently taken is is basically
something that hustler handles for you
so if you want to kind of look at
enhanced api security you want to look
at certain methods of governance you
want to look at performance slas and
those are the kinds of features you want
to look at observability or monitoring
integrations with their existing stack
right those are the kinds of features
that are then available in our
commercial versions so that you know the
build and the api experience is the same
across both you can switch back and
forth between the two but as soon as you
come to kind of some of those
investments on the devops sdlc and
upside of things that you'd rather not
bother with because it's not it's
necessary for your business but you
don't want to do it right that's the
part that makes for you okay so you'll
see that on our commercial versions and
people can get started and then they can
grow up into either a cloud hosted or a
enterprise edition as the need arises
exactly and there's a perpetual free
tier on cloud as well so you know just
sign up point it to your thing and you
should be up and running in 30 seconds
that's great docker compose up and you
know just here you go
you're you're doing the graphql thing
exactly anything else about hasero or
graphql that we've missed that you want
to make sure listeners know about just
asking listeners to try out give us
feedback on what their experience with
graphql industrial was like would be
great and to watch out for some of the
new streaming subscriptions work that
we're doing that allows people to stream
billions of records over a graphql api
for data heavy apis that's going to be
very exciting that's something that
we're going to be talking about soon
okay very interesting
and if listeners want to find out more
about what you're up to where should
they go hustler.io is the best place to
the best portal the starting portal to
go into the different universes
active forums are our discord forum and
github forums that's kind of where you
can hang with other developers and other
users talk about where i should use
hasura where i can use graphql talk to
the hospital engineers itself and of
course please always at any point of
time feel free you reach out to me i'm
pretty responsive on twitter and on
linkedin okay and your twitter is tan my
go t-a-n-m-a-i-g-o
on twitter and then also you blog at
hasura.io that's
h-a-s-u-r-a dot io slash blog slash at
symbol
tan my g t a n m a i g
is that right yep okay great that's
perfect well tamar thank you so much for
joining us today on software engineering
radio it's great having you thank you so
much for having me jeff it was a great
conversation great this is jeff
doolittle for software engineering radio
thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening